<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vindiciæ sacræ. A treatise of the honor and maintenance due to ecclesiasticall persons. Done out of the Latin, of that famous diuine of Holland, H. Saravia, sometime prebend of Canterbury.</title>
            <title>De diversis ministrorum evangelii gradibus. Part 3. English</title>
            <author>Saravia, Adrien, 1530-1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112329</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847584</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847584</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1609:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vindiciæ sacræ. A treatise of the honor and maintenance due to ecclesiasticall persons. Done out of the Latin, of that famous diuine of Holland, H. Saravia, sometime prebend of Canterbury.</title>
                  <title>De diversis ministrorum evangelii gradibus. Part 3. English</title>
                  <author>Saravia, Adrien, 1530-1612.</author>
                  <author>Martin, James, fl. 1615-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Cotes and R. Cotes for Iames Boler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by James Martin, of part 3 of: Saravia, Adrien.  De diversis ministrorum evangelii gradibus.</note>
                  <note>"An appendix to Sarauia, ansvvering fovre maine arguments which vsurpers of the churches right vsually alledge" has separate dated title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Office --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sacrilege --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>VINDICIAE SACRAE. A <hi>TREATISE OF THE</hi> Honor and Maintenance due to <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Done out of the Latin, of that famous Diuine of <hi>Holland,</hi> H. SARAVIA, ſometime Prebend of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ECCLESIAST. 7.31.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Feare the Lord, and honour the Prieſt: and giue him his Portion, as it is commanded thee.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>L. COKE Reports. B. Wincheſt. Caſe.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Le decay des reuenues de homes de Saint Eſgliſe, in le fine ſerra ſubuerſion del ſeruice de Dieu, &amp; de ſon Religion.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>The decay of the Reueneues of men of the holy Church; will, in the end, be the ſubuerſion of Gods Seruice and Religion.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the ſame Caſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Diſmes ſont choſes ſpiritual, &amp; due de iure Diuino.</q>
                  <q>Tithes are ſpirituall things, and due by the Law of God,</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Cotes</hi> and <hi>R. Cotes</hi> for <hi>Iames Boler,</hi> 1629.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>TO THE ILLVSTRIOVS PRINCESSE, THE DVCHESSE OF BVCKINGHAM: WHOM GOD</hi> PRESERVE.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your GRACE:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR moſt Noble and pious Diſpoſition (to omit other Motiues and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligements) hath embolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to preſent You this Treatiſe, (writ in behalfe of the Clergie:) which in all proſtrate humilitie is here tendred to your Gracious Acceptance. Great is the Honor and Eminence, to which God hath exalted you; and will be yet much greater, if you honor him (againe) in his Prophets and Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors; who are (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth)
<pb facs="tcp:12623:3"/>worthy of double honor;
<note place="margin">Tim. 5.7.</note> and are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by our bleſſed Sauiour, and his Holy Spirit, with theſe glorious Titles, <hi>The Light of the World.
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.14 Reu. 1.20.</note> The Starres &amp; Angels of the Church. The Charrets and Horſemen of Iſrael.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Kin. 2.12</note> Which the Deuil well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſometime endeauours to eclipſe their Splendor, and poyſon their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, by the venemous Tongues of wicked Miſcreants: otherwhile, total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to extinguiſh and ruinate them, by the curſed plots and perſecutions of bloody Tyrants: by whom, he common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſes to diſcharge his great Artillery againſt them; who being once cut off, it muſt needs exceedingly enlarge his Kingdome of Darkneſſe. Thus in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient time, that <hi>BASILISKE, Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> being mounted on the Imperiall
<pb facs="tcp:12623:3"/>Throne, most cruelly maſſacred the Prieſts and Paſtors of the Church. Yet this Murthering-piece (in the iuſt cenſure of a famous learned Lawyer) was not ſo preiudiciall to Chriſtianity,
<note place="margin">L. Coke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Winch. ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> as that <hi>SERPENTINE,</hi> Julian <hi>the Apoſtate, who (as Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories report) ſlew &amp; marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the verie Prieſthood it ſelfe: for he rob'd the Church, &amp; ſtript Spirituall perſons of their Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues. Whereupon enſued great Ignorance, and extreme decay of Chriſtian Religion; there being none that would apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or Children, or any they had in charge, to the ſtudy of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, when they ſaw that after long and painfull ſtudie, they ſhould haue nothing to liue on.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12623:4"/>(Thus farre, that Oracle and Miracle of the Law.) And hence it was, that in the laſt Age and Centenarie, that great red Dragon,
<note place="margin">Reu. 12.3.</note> whoſe name, is a Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>(Reuel. 9.11.)</hi> was ſo buſie in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enating the Churches Patrimonie, in demoliſhing her goodly Manſions, and Monuments, and in conuerting the Houſes of God into Stables, (or worſe:) and all vnder a faire colour of
<note place="margin">Non rem, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed modum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> mno.)</note> 
                     <hi>REFORMATION</hi> (which certen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is a good word; but it hath ſerued to gild many a rotten poſt.) And this ſtill is the Diuels Method and manner of proceeding, where he gets to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant, and finds fit and actiue In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for his purpoſe. Jt was well obſerued by a
<note place="margin">5 Ben Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Noble Knight in his Speech to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, the laſt Seſsion: That
<pb facs="tcp:12623:4"/>
                     <hi>although the Calling of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, were neuer ſo glorious within, yet outward pouertie would bring contempt vpon them; eſpecially among thoſe who meaſure men by the acre, and weigh them by the pound (as moſt doe.) Which (he ſaid) he found by experience in</hi> Germany, <hi>where hee ſaw the ſtipendarie Miniſters of the Reformed Churches deſpiſed &amp; neglected by reaſon of their pouertie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (otherwiſe) very graue and learned men.</hi> And there is no doubt <hi>(MADAM)</hi> but it is the maine drift and maſterpeece of Satan, and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall Engines, and Emiſſaries (at this day) to reduce the Preachers of Gods ſacred Word here in <hi>England,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12623:5"/>to the like penurious and deſpicable Eſtate, thereby to euacuate the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of their Calling, and vtterly to annihilate their perſons &amp; Doctrine, (For <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, a man of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red graces, a diuine Prophet, and mightie Warrior, yet (in King <hi>Saul</hi>'s time) profeſt, that being a poore man, hee was but lightly eſteemed, <hi>1 Sam. 18.23.</hi>) To preuent therefore this dangerous ſtratagem, and cunning ſleight of the old Serpent; it is the duty of all good Chriſtians reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, eſpecially of thoſe whom God hath bleſſed with Honor, Wealth, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to giue all due Honor, Ayd, and Support to the choſen Meſſengers and Embaſſadours of the King of Heauen; whoſe ſacred and honorable Function was once in better eſteeme
<pb facs="tcp:12623:5"/>with the World, when a Priest mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed a Kings Daughter (For ſo it is recorded, <hi>2 Chronic. 22.11.</hi> viz. <hi>Iehoſhabeth the Daughter of King Iehoram, the Wife of Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iada the Prieſt.)</hi> As for thoſe proud Phariſaicall Peacockes,
<note place="margin">Tit.</note> which <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe</hi> that they know God, but in workes deny him, and in a pretended zeale to the Goſpel, make Stales and Pack-horſes of their Preachers, and yet rob them of their Maintenance; (ſcarſe affording them, the crummes that fall from their Worſhips Tables) they ſhall (without due Repentance, and Restitution) one day know and feele, that the prophane contempt, and baſe entertainment of them, rebounds vpon Chriſt which ſent them: for ſo himſelfe proclaimes, <hi>Luke 10.16.
<pb facs="tcp:12623:6"/>Hee that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me.</hi> Vndoubtedly, theſe ſelf-conceited Humoriſts, and Solifidian-Nullifidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of our Time, haue by their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious dealing, and irreligious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour towards their ſpirituall Guides, made themſelues worſe then Heathens and Barbarians: For how carefull was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (a Heathen King) in the extremitie of Famine, to prouide for his Prieſts, and preſerue their Lands from Sale or Alienation? <hi>Gen. 47.22.</hi> And what wonderfull kind, yea <hi>Honorable</hi> Entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did the Barbarians ſhew to S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and his diſtreſſed Companie? (See <hi>Acts 28. verſ. 2, 7, 10.</hi>) Which memorable Examples, the Spirit of God hath not regiſtred in vaine; but for our Inſtruction, and the Conuiction
<pb facs="tcp:12623:6"/>of their execrable Impietie, which in their hungry zeale, gape after the ſpoyle and ruine of the Church. Yet (to giue theſe Hypocrites their due) they are content that <hi>the Kings Daughter</hi> (the Church Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue) be <hi>all glorious within;</hi> but,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 45.14</note> that <hi>her Cloathing</hi> ſhould bee <hi>of wrought Gold;</hi> fie, they hold it very vnfitting: Jt were <hi>(ſay they)</hi> farre more decent and commendable for the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall State</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and ſute it ſelfe to the Apostles Pouertie, and to that pure and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Time. This, <hi>they thinke,</hi> is a Seraphicall Speculation, and worthy our best Attention: And J doubt not, but the Church will be content to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this <hi>Conformitie,</hi> vpon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that (according to <hi>the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:12623:7"/>Rule, and Example</hi> of the deuout Chriſtians of that Age) theſe <hi>Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Religion,</hi> and all other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Christianitie will instantly ſell all they haue, and lay downe the price at the Churches feet, <hi>Act. 4.34.</hi> Surely <hi>(MADAM)</hi> were theſe People <hi>in truth</hi> the Children of God (as they ſtrongly fancie themſelues; <hi>Narciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſ-like,</hi> being in loue with their owne ſuppoſed Beauty) they would be better affected to the Church (the Miſtreſſe of heauenly <hi>Truth</hi>) and not goe about (like pernicious Furies) to cloathe Her in Raggs; that ſo feruently and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently endeuors (by the dispenſation of Gods holy Word and Sacraments) to adorne their Soules with the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pearles, and inestimable Jewels of all Chriſtian Vertues; and to inuest
<pb facs="tcp:12623:7"/>them (<note place="margin">Luke</note> 
                     <hi>primâ ſtolâ</hi>) with the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embrodered Robes, and Royall Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a true, iuſtifying, and ſauing Faith. But they well ſhew of what <hi>Spirit</hi> they are: euen of <hi>ſuch a one,</hi> as would fright the whole <hi>Packe</hi> of them, if he ſhould appeare and briſtle among them at their Conuenticles, or Night-Aſſemblies.</p>
                  <p>The GOD of Heauen aſsiſt and comfort your <hi>GRACE</hi> with his <hi>Holy Spirit;</hi> make you a happy Jnſtrument of much Good to his Church; and crowne you (in the end) with a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem of eternall <hi>GLORIE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your GRACES moſt humbly deuoted, IAMES MARTIN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:8"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:8"/>
                  <head>TO ALL NOBLE AND RELIGIOVS <hi>Patrons and Patroneſſes</hi> of the CHVRCH.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Noble and Religious:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET it not ſeeme ſtrange to ioyne you all in one Inſcription, whom God hath linked (as thoſe ancient Worthies and
<note place="margin">Act. 4.32.</note> primitiue Saints) by the Golden Chaine of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Societie and Communion, for the comfort and ſupport of his deſpiſed and diſtreſſed <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors;</hi> whom, though the Deuil, &amp; his Aethiopian Angels,
<note place="margin">Reu. 2.10.</note> ſtriue continually (by their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, and <hi>Vnder-minisbers</hi>) to bring into Aegyptian ſeruitude
<pb facs="tcp:12623:9"/>and contempt, by oppreſsing, deprauing, and impoueriſhing them; yet hath the Spirit of GRACE ſtirred vp your excellent Spirits, to relieue, encourage, and ſuſtaine them. In which Noble Actions (among other famous Precedents) you haue that thrice-Glorious Emperor THEODOSIVS, your Predeceſſor; who euen on his Death-bed, and in extremitie of Sickneſſe, expreſt his Royall Charitie, ardent Zeale, &amp; feruent Deuotion to the State Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall: as (to his eternall honor) S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hath recorded. And ſurely, if ſome
<note place="margin">Tim. 3.5.</note> ſelfe-deceauing Chriſtians of our Time (which make Religion a verie Mumme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and Diſguiſe for their ſiniſter
<pb facs="tcp:12623:9"/>ends, and giue ſmall or no
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Diuine Ordinance in the Miniſterie of their owne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors) would <hi>vn-maske</hi> a while, and enter into a ſtrict conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Mortalitie, and the infiniteneſſe of Eternitie; with the ſucceeding interminable Ioyes or Torments they muſt ſhortly endure; how highly would they eſteeme and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence their <hi>'Rectors,</hi> and <hi>Spirituall Guides, (Heb.</hi> 13.17.) whom God hath ſo ſingularly honord with that <hi>Euangelicall,</hi> yea <hi>Angelicall</hi> Office of conducting Soules to Heauen? Would they not (in a ſacred Rapture) cry out with the Propheticall
<note place="margin">Eſay 52.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Euangeliſt; <hi>How beautifull vpon the Mountaines are
<pb facs="tcp:12623:10"/>the feet of him that declareth and publiſheth Peace: that declareth good tidings; and publiſheth Saluation, ſaying vnto Zion, Thy God raigneth.</hi> Vndoubtedly, they would (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their humane frailties, and
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cor. 4.7.</note> infirmities) receiue them as the
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.13, 14, 15.</note> 
                     <hi>Galatians</hi> did S. <hi>Paul:</hi> and thinke nothing too good, or too precious for them. But (alas!) we haue too iuſt cauſe to <hi>ſubioine</hi> that of the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16. <hi>All haue not obeyed the Goſpel.</hi> For many (ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) will goe with the <hi>Wiſe-men</hi> from the Eaſt,
<note place="margin">Act. 2.11.</note> to <hi>ſeeke</hi> Chriſt, yea they will <hi>fall down and worſhip</hi> him, but they are growne <hi>too wiſe</hi> to open their <hi>Treaſures.</hi> Bleſſed therefore are YOV (thrice-Noble Chriſtians)
<pb facs="tcp:12623:10"/>that ſpare neither your <hi>Gold, Frankincenſe,</hi> nor <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> but make your Riches (as <hi>Abraham</hi> did his Seruants) to helpe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine the <hi>Angels</hi> of God. And thrice-bleſſed ſhall you be at that <hi>GREAT DAY,</hi> when you ſhall ioyntly receaue your <hi>GREAT REWARD</hi> in Heauen. March on therefore (like the Starres in their Orbes, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.20.) in your <hi>Seraphicall Zeale</hi> to the Houſe of God, and the Officers thereof; that by ſuch Heauenly Acts of Pietie, <hi>laying vp in ſtore for your ſelues a good
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.19.</note> Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation againſt the time to come, you may lay hold on Eternall Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The God of Heauen multiply the Glorious Graces of his Holy
<pb facs="tcp:12623:11"/>Spirit vpon you; that being <hi>faithfull vnto Death,
<note place="margin">Reu. 2.10.</note> He may giue you a Crowne of Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Veſter humilis &amp; deuotus; IACOBVS MARTINIVS. <hi>Facultatis Artium</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Oxon.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:11"/>
                  <head>DE <hi>Authore &amp; Jnterprete</hi> CARMEN.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>QVae priùs in Latio</l>
                     <l>latuerunt, abdita vulgo,</l>
                     <l>Dogmata Semonis</l>
                     <l>ſancta &amp; celebranda Bataui,</l>
                     <l>Haec ſacer Interpres</l>
                     <l>pulcrè transfundit, &amp; ornat.</l>
                     <l>At qui ſacrata</l>
                     <l>&amp; gemmata monilia Libro</l>
                     <l>Explicat aureolo,</l>
                     <l>Gemmam proponit in illo.</l>
                     <l>E. Gemmam. Ne ſis</l>
                     <l>Aeſopi (Lector) <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>RICHARDVS CRVXONIVS <hi>Theologus.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_author">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:12"/>
                  <head>To the AVTHOR.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>AS ſome rare Flower;</l>
                     <l>whoſe ſilken Leaues haue beene</l>
                     <l>Concealed long</l>
                     <l>from their deſired View,</l>
                     <l>Diſplayes (at last)</l>
                     <l>his bright-ſweet-ſmiling hew,</l>
                     <l>Fit to adorne</l>
                     <l>the Boſome of a Queene:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Or as a Diamond</l>
                     <l>of rich esteeme,</l>
                     <l>In doubtfull ſhadow</l>
                     <l>of the darkeſome Night;</l>
                     <l>Darts forth his beames,</l>
                     <l>and giues a cheerfull light;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Luſtre may</l>
                     <l>a Royall Crowne beſeeme:</l>
                     <l>So ſhine thy Glories;</l>
                     <l>ſo this Worke ſhall be</l>
                     <l>An Arch-Triumphall</l>
                     <l>to thy Memorie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. B. LONDINAS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12623:12"/>
                  <head>A Treatiſe of the honor and maintenance due to the CLERGIE.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. I. </hi>Donaries giuen to Churches, are firme by the ſame Lawes, by which others of the Laity poſſeſſe their eſtates.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE zeale and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our fore Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in enriching the Church are knowne to all: and it were ſtrange to imagine that an vniuerſall er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, or (as ſome would haue it) a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhould ſo long tranſport them in that point; and that their Poſteritie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12623:13"/>going a quite contrary way, without Warrant from God, and Example of former Ages, ſhould bee wiſer then they. As to follow the bad examples of our Anceſtors is a fond Abſurdity; ſo to contemne their examples raſhly and without iuſt cauſe, is meere Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety. It is true, both fathers and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, are all prone to euill; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are men, more apt to take from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or to giue of their owne? Our fathers gaue (as none can deny) with no ill intent: their children take away what they gaue; with what minde, is apparant enough. They gaue, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes; theſe take, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Law. Thoſe things which haue beene giuen to the Church, haue their ſtrength and validity from the ſelfe-ſame Lawes whereby other men poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe what they haue: and there is none, but would thinke it a Tyrannicall act in a Magiſtrate, to thurſt him out of his Poſſeſſions, without hearing him firſt ſpeake for himſelfe.</p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12623:13"/>
                     <p>It had beene fit therefore that Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons ſhould haue beene permitted to haue had audience; and that ſufficient reaſons ſhould haue been alleaged to them why they ought not any longer to be ſuffered in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Common wealth, nor to enioy the poſſeſſions of the Church. They alſo which ſucceeded them in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall Charge, ſhould haue beene heard: for it concerned them to know how the goods of the Church were diſpoſed. But to confiſcate and ſweepe all away, without any legall procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or hearing of the parties, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all right and reaſon. If Biſhops and Prieſts were willing to renounce Popery and embrace the Truth, there was no cauſe to expell them; vnleſſe perhaps Church-Liuings were to bee numbered among the Hereſies and Idolatries of the Romiſh Church: as ſome good fellowes would haue them.</p>
                     <p>And here, I know not whether the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12623:14"/>Ignorance of Miniſters, or the Auarice of Magiſtrats, be more blame-worthy: Both, without queſtion were very faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But thoſe ſubtle and crafty Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques which hypocritically made a faire ſhew to fauour the preaching of the Goſpell, for their owne baſe and wicked ends, were the Authors and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors of all this miſchiefe: So that, what in others was Error or Ignorance, in them was pure Malice and Villany. For who can excuſe them of ſacriledge which vnder colour of reforming the Church in many places of High and Low Germany, made a prey of all that was giuen to the Church? I confeſſe, the ſupreme Magiſtrate ought to be the Patron of the Church, and may by his authoritie enact Lawes concerning Church-liuings, but in no caſe, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate them to himſelf. For the Patron ought not to diſpoyle his Clyent: And it was neuer heard of before theſe Times, that any Chriſtian Magiſtrate did confiſcate all Eccleſiaſticall Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12623:14"/>without exception. All Hiſtories haue branded them with Infamy which in Extremities of the Commonwealth haue taken away but a part: What then ſhall we thinke of thoſe which haue playd at ſweepe-ſtake with Church-Liuings? I name none, but I meane them, which by their lewd Examples haue taught their Neighbours to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Sacriledge: Wherein they imitate <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, and the great <hi>Turke</hi> (which make no difference betwixt ſacred and prophane) and not any Chriſtian Magiſtrate either of theſe or former times, that I know. To ſuch, it is a ſhame that Sacriledge may iuſtly be obiected: But a farre greater ſhame that by ſuch it ſhould be vniuſtly committed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12623:15"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II. </hi>The definition of Sacriledge.</head>
                     <p>SOme there are that thinke no Sacriledge can be now commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe (forſooth) the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt ſacred and prophane, in externall things, is by our Sauiours death extinguiſht. But this is not the opinion of a Diuine, but of an Atheiſt rather. For though to the holy, all things be holy; and all things prophane to the prophane; yet the diſtinction of Things which they haue in their vſe and end, is not to be aboliſht. Among all Nations, there was euer a maine difference ſet betwixt that which was dedicated to Diuine worſhip, and that which was for vulgar vſe. It is the End, which (for the moſt part) denominates all things. Priuate men haue their Treaſure: and the Common-wealth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12623:15"/>hers: If you regard the ſtuffe, both are of the ſame nature (to wit, Gold and Siluer, and whatſoeuer elſe is of value) But if you reſpect the End, and Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor; it is farre otherwiſe: For the end of priuate wealth, is the profite of one onely Family: But the end of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, is the benefite of the Prince and People. In like ſort, the Treaſure or Wealth which is giuen or collected for the Worſhip of God, hath a farre different end from the other: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſecrated to a holy vſe, is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſacred.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore, as the Wrong againſt the Prince or State is more heynous, then that againſt a priuate man: And therefore the ſtealing from a priuate man is but Theft; but from the publike Treaſurie,
<note place="margin">Pecula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Robberie in the higheſt degree: So by how much more it is a greater crime to ſinne againſt GOD then Man, the expilation of the ſacred Portion is farre more damnable then any other Theft or Robberie whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12623:16"/>And therefore it is properly termed Sacriledge; and is defined, The ſtealing of a thing ſacred. The turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of which Theft is ſo execrable, that God himſelfe &amp; all Nations haue puniſht it with exquiſite Torments. But the former definition compriſes not onely things deſtinate to the ſeruice of the true GOD, but alſo of falſe Gods. For the Knowledge and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of any Deitie, is of the Eſſence of Sacriledge: Now that all, or the moſt which Popiſh Clergie poſſeſſed either by the Poore, or Churches inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, hath beene purloyned, ſold, confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, or conuerted to priuate mens vſes; it is ſo cleere, that I need not ſtand further vpon it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:12623:16"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III. </hi>Reaſons or Pretenſes where-with ſome would palliate their Sacriledge.</head>
                     <p>BVT ſacrilegious Perſons and their Proctors contend, that whatſoeuer was done in this caſe, was lawfully done, both for the aboliſhing of the Popes Tyrannie; and for the eſtabliſhing of the Goſpell. Their Reaſons are theſe. Eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſions were imploied to idolatrous and prophane vſes, which being abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, they cannot by the Lawes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to any, but onely to the publike Treaſurie; the gouernment whereof belongs to the Chriſtian Magiſtrate. And as the godly Emperors <hi>Conſtantin, Theodoſius, Honorius,</hi> and <hi>Arcadius,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing baniſhed the Idolatry of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> tooke into their hands (without any note of Sacriledge) the Reuenewes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12623:17"/>and Poſſeſſions of their Prieſts and Temples, to diſpoſe, as pleaſed them: So alſo the Chriſtian Magiſtrate ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing caſhierd Popery, may by the ſame Right challenge the Wealth and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which belonged to Prieſts, Monkes, Nunnes, and the like; and confiſcate them, as Eſcheats vſually are; according to Law. For no Biſhop euer thought that the Church had any Right or Title to thoſe Goods or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes which were deſtinated to Idolatry: Strange therefore it were that any Miniſter of the Goſpel ſhould clayme the Riches of the Popiſh Church as due to the Reformed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, there is extant an Imperiall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree in the Court, in the firſt Booke <hi>De Paganis &amp; Sacrificijs, tit.</hi> 14. in theſe words: <hi>Omnia loca, &amp;c.</hi> that is: Wee command that all places which the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Ancients aſſigned to Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, be appropriated to our Eſtate. But that which We or the Princes our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors haue (by that Right) beſtowed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12623:17"/>on particular perſons, Wee will that it be perpetually confirmed to them, as their Patrimonie. And thoſe things, which We are pleaſed by many Edicts to allot to the Church, let the Chriſtian Religion challenge as her owne. Dated at <hi>Rauenna</hi> 3 <hi>Cal. Sept. Honorius</hi> the 10, and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the 6, Emperors. By which Decree, it is manifeſt, that the Emperours had right to diſpoſe to whom they pleaſed, thoſe Goods which after the abrogation of the Idolatry of Pagans, had no owners. And in the <hi>Digest. Lib.</hi> 33. <hi>tit.</hi> 2. <hi>De vſu &amp; vſu fructu legatis leg.</hi> 16. <hi>Legatum, &amp;c.</hi> We read of Legacies beſtowed vpon Showes or Playes which were not lawfull to bee acted: And if the word Maſſe bee put in ſtead of the word Playes, the caſe will be alike. The words of the Law are thus: <hi>Legatum Ciuitati relictum, &amp;c.</hi> that is: A Legacie being bequeathed to a Citie, to the end that out of the yeerely Reuenewes a Show be exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Citie in memorie of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12623:18"/>which is vnlawfull to be done; I demand what your opinion is of ſuch a Legacie? <hi>Modestinus</hi> anſwers thus: Whereas the Teſtator would haue a publike Show in the Citie, but ſuch a one as is not lawfull to be celebrated, it were vniuſt that ſo great a ſumme of Money which the defunct had deſtined to that end, ſhould fall to his heyres. Wherefore his heyres and the chieſe of the Citie being called together, let them aduiſe to what other vſe the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacie may be conuerted; that the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtators memorie may by ſome other lawfull meanes be preſerued. Thus <hi>Modestinus Lib. 9. Reſponſorum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By which Law it is eaſie to iudge what wee are to thinke of thoſe Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies which are left for ſaying of Maſſes.</p>
                     <p>Moreouer, the Couetouſneſſe of Clergie-men was ſo vnſatiable, that they procured infinite ſuperſtitious Gifts and Legacies beyond all ſtint and meaſure.</p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12623:18"/>
                     <p>And when the peoples Liberalitie began to fayle, they bought Lands, Mannors, and ſometimes whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys: Inſomuch, that at laſt they would haue gotten the whole Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World into their poſſeſſion, had not Kings and Emperors (ſeeing the dammage which their States were like to ſuſtaine) limited and reſtrayned them by their Lawes. It concernes therefore wiſe Magiſtrates to looke about them, leſt they ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the ſame Stone.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12623:19"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IIII. </hi>An Anſwer to the Reaſons layd downe in the former Chapter.</head>
                     <p>IN Anſwer whereof, We are to take heed, leaſt auoyding one extreme we run (like Fooles) into the other. If we iudge, our Fore-fathers were too profuſe, ought not their Error admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs that we alſo are Men, and that it is eaſier to fall into the contrarie vice, then to keepe a meane? And that the ſtreame of Auarice and baſe niggardiſe may tranſport vs too farre? For admit, that the Clergie (if the Lawes of Chriſtian Princes had not bridled them) would haue heaped vp infinite wealth, to the great derriment of the Land, and that many things giuen them were partly ſuperſtitiouſly beſtowed, partly more then needed: It followes not, that therefore none of thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12623:19"/>made to the Church, were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, pious, well-pleaſing to God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to his Word, and profitable and neceſſarie for his Church. If there were in thoſe things any thing ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, it might be pared away: And what was conſigned to Superſtition and Idolatry, might (with them) be abrogated, or put to better vſes. But whereas they ſay, that what was done in that kind, was wholly for the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Popiſh Tyrannie, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the Goſpell; it is a meere pretext. For the truth is, a ſort of craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Knaues, groſſely abuſing the Goſpel, and the Preachers thereof (whom they eaſily perſwaded) made hauocke of the Churches Eſtate, which I will not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeake of: For if I ſtirre this Dung-hill, the ſent will be intolerable. Let vs now examine what hath beene alledged in defence of Sacriledge. Firſt, it is ſayd, that the Reuenewes of the Church did maintaine Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Idolatry: which being baniſht,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12623:20"/>they could not by the Lawes come to any, but to the publike Treaſurie. But to diſcouer the fallacie of this Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I affirme that there is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt Things deſtinated to Impious and Idolatrous vſes, and thoſe Things which Men abuſe to Luxurie or Impietie. There is nothing ſo ſacred which wicked Men will not abuſe. The Abuſe of a good thing alters not its Nature: neither were all the Riches of the Church of Rome giuen her to bad and vnlawfull Ends. For much was giuen heretofore for the ſupport of Church-Miniſters, and the Poore: which though it were abuſed by the Romiſh Clergie, yet the propertie of thoſe Donaries was not quite changed thereby. Of Donations made to Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſome praeceded the corrupt times of the Church; others, followed after. For it is certaine that the Faithfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to contribute to the Church euen at the firſt planting thereof, in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times. Now thoſe which praeceded the corruption of the Church, none
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12623:20"/>can deny but were conſecrated to God. The Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes found the Church planted by the Apoſtles, and endowed with a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent eſtate (conſidering the times) whereto though they did by vnlawfull meanes adde much more: yet is not all that to be vtterly condemned: but the End thereof, to be regarded. For in the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> and other Hereticall Churches, are many things, which, conſidered aright in their kind, are truly Chriſtian and commanded by God: ſuch as are, the ſacred Miniſterie of the Church: and Prouiſion for the Poore. Now whatſoeuer was giuen to either or both of theſe, was vndoubtedly giuen to a pious end, and might haue a ſanctified vſe. We ought therefore not ſo much to looke to the prophanation of them, as to the Qualitie of the Things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to which, no man, either by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, or continued abuſe, can pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe any Right. But if it chance that the prophane or Idolatrous vſe be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht, they ought to returne to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12623:21"/>and lawfull vſe. The Arke of God was taken and abuſed by the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims,</hi> yet it did not therefore ceaſe to be conſecrated to God: and being af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſent home by the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> it was as much to be reſpected, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The Veſſels and Ornaments of <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple, were carryed by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzer</hi> to <hi>Babylon:</hi> where he put them into the Temple of his Gods: and (in his manner) did religiouſſy eſteeme of them. Now when <hi>Cyrus</hi> had taken <hi>Babylon,</hi> he might by the right of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, haue made clayme to them: but vnderſtanding that they did ſometime appertaine to the Diuine Worſhip in <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple, he durſt not meddle with them, but commanded them to be reſtored to their former vſe: leſt hee ſhould fall into the ſame ſinne of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for which God had puniſht <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar.</hi> Thoſe things therefore which in a pious intent, were once giuen to the Church, are conſecrated to God: and may not lawfully be transferred to other vſes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12623:21"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. V. </hi>A Triple difference of Eccleſiasticall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes poſſeſt by the Romane Church at this day.</head>
                     <p>BVt whereas all the Endowments of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are not of the ſame kind, wee ought not to iudge of them all alike. There is a three-fold difference of them. In the firſt Ranke I put thoſe things which our Anceſtors gaue for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Church-Miniſters, and the Poore: Next, what was giuen ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly, as for Maſſing for the Quicke and Dead, and whatſoeuer was bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed to Monkes, Nunnes, and Soule-Prieſts: Laſtly, I reckon thoſe infinite Donaries, pernicious to the State of Chriſtendome, which were vnaduiſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen by Kings and Emperors, or by force or fraud extorted from them: of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12623:22"/>which ſort are Inueſtitures of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Feudes, giuen by Princes to the Church, and in that regard, belonging thereto; which neuertheleſſe the Pope claymes as his Right: As alſo thoſe Kingdomes which are made tributarie to the Pope: wherein he challenges a perpetuitie. I ſpeake not of the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of the whole World, which hee likewiſe makes claime to. Theſe things ſince by diuine and humane Right they pertaine to Kings, the things which are <hi>Caeſars</hi> ought to be reſtored to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> For our Lord hath forbidden the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his Church, to be Kings, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.25. where he thus corrects the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of his Apoſtles: Kings of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> exerciſe Lordſhip ouer them, and they that are in authoritie ouer them are called Benefactors; But ye ſhall not be ſo: That is, You ſhall not be Kings: whom, thoſe that are vnder their cruell gouernment, are fayne to flatter with the magnificall Titles of Clemencie and Beneficence. Iuſtly therefore may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12623:22"/>Kings reſume whatſoeuer the Romane Prelate hath fraudulently or violently appropriated to himſelfe. But in this point there is both Prudence and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to be vſed, leſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> take not (with his own due) thoſe things which belong to God. The Romane Clergie ſeiz'd on both: And it were a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour for the Chriſtian Magiſtrate to imitate them; and to puniſh Rapine with Sacriledge. I grant, thar the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may by his Authoritie diſpoſe at his pleaſure thoſe things which were giuen to meerly ſuperſtitious and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous vſes, and that the Church hath no Right to them. Notwithſtanding, if the Law before recited, or the Aduice of moſt learned <hi>Augustine</hi> may take place, the Legacies bequeathed to the ſaying of Maſſes, or the ſuſtayning of Fryers and Nunnes, may be conuerted to better vſes, whereby, the Teſtators memorie may be lawfully perpetuated. In the 16 chap. of <hi>Numbers,</hi> the Cenſers (wherewith 250 Rebelles, impiouſly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12623:23"/>vſurping vpon the Prieſthood, would needs offer Incenſe to God) were hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: And therefore God would not haue them afterwards employed to common vſes, but commanded that they ſhould be made into broad Plates for a couering of the Altar, that ſo the Braſſe which they had wickedly abuſed might be put to a ſacred vſe. Which Command, though it be not generall, yet it teacheth vs what to doe in the like caſe. <hi>Augustine</hi> in his 154 Epiſtle to <hi>Publicola,</hi> concerning the Euerſion of Idols, and their Groues, and Temples; iudgeth that they were to be conuerted not to priuate vſes (leſt it ſhould ſeeme to haue beene done rather by Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, then Deuotion) but to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; and namely, to the Seruice of the true God: That ſo, they might be in the ſame ſtate with Men, that from prophane Impietie were conuerted to Chriſtianitie.</p>
                     <p>Since the Law of God preſcribes nothing herein to the Magiſtrate in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12623:23"/>expreſſe tearmes; and whatſoeuer <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> hath written hereof, concernes the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in particular; for my part, I am of opinion that he may vſe his own Diſcretion in the managing of theſe things: Nor doe I contradict the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Emperours <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius:</hi> Yet I would deſire that Princes and other Soueraigne Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates which haue reformed the Church would conſider, that Abbyes and Monaſteries did robbe her of her Right when they impropriated to themſelues the Tithes and Offerings which Chriſtian Princes and People did in times paſt conſecrate to their Paſtor and the Poore. For contrarie to the cuſtome of the ancient Church, they tooke vpon them the gouernment of Churches; and vnder colour of profeſt Pouertie, they ſnatcht away thoſe things which ought to haue beene diſtributed to the Poore indeed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12623:24"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VI. </hi>The poſſeſsions of Monkes are not all of like nature.</head>
                     <p>AS I haue ſhewed the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the Eſtate of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors &amp; Rectorsof the Church: ſo alſo are the Poſſeſſions of Monkes not all alike. It were tedious to recount how they came to ſo great Wealth: This chiefely would I haue obſerued, that whatſoeuer was poſſeſt by Monks, that was indeed due to the Poore, and Church-Paſtors, doth appertaine to the firſt ſort of Eccleſiaſticall goods, which after the Ouerthrow of Monkerie, are not to be held as eſcheated, while the Church hath Paſtors and Poore to prouide for. Wherefore after the Eie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Poperie, thoſe things onely were to be confiſcate, which did onely ſerue to ſupport the Popes Superſtition
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12623:24"/>or Tyrannie. The remainder, which had no impious Ground or End, ſhould haue beene reſtored to the Church. Whereſoeuer therefore all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to Monkes and Monaſteries was confiſcate by the conſent or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of thoſe whom it more neerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to looke to it, they were the more too blame, that did not intercede therein; and better informe the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate: for ſurely, the prophanation and abuſe of the Churches Patrimonic, could not be ſo great, as to change the nature of it, and vtterly deſtroy the firſt Donation. The Arke of God among the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> was ſtill the ſame: and the Veſſels of the Temple, loſt not their ſanctitie in <hi>Babylon.</hi> What though the Pope and his Clergie fouly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly abuſed the true and lawfull Goods of the Church? Ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore the true Miniſters of the Church to be cheated and defrauded of them? Their Poſſeſſors, are not Lords or Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of them; but Stewards onely,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12623:25"/>hauing the vſe, fruit and adminiſtration of the Churches Eſtate, but no propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie therein. Neither makes it any thing againſt me, that Biſhops in times paſt thought that the Reuenewes dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to Pagan Gods, did not belong (of right) to the Church; for I ſay not, that the Church hath any Title to thoſe Things which were immediately dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to Impietie: ſuch, I haue already confeſſed to be in the power, and at the donation of the Magiſtrate: and that the Edict of <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and other pious Emperors and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Kings diſpleaſeth not mee: Whoſe Examples, if they, whoſe Errors moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to write this Treatiſe, would haue vouchſafed to haue followed; there had been no need of this Diſputation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12623:25"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VII. </hi>It is one thing for People to be conuerted from Paganiſme to Chriſtianitie: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, from Poperie, or any other Hereſie.</head>
                     <p>WEE may not forget, that it is a farre other matter for any People to paſſe from the Pagan Religion to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; then from the Papiſticall Hereſie to the ſame. The Difference betwixt Paganiſme and Chriſtianiſme is not the ſame as betweene Papiſme and Chriſtianiſme. For Paganiſme hath in it nothing at all of Chriſtianitie: but Poperie is Chriſtianitie contaminated with Superſtition and Idolatry, and (as I may ſay) a Mungrell and impure Chriſtianiſme. For the holy Scripture of the old and new Teſtament, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of God, the Baptiſme of Chriſt,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12623:26"/>the Remiſſion of Sinnes, the Name of Chriſtian, and many other things there are in it that are proper to the Church, and Markes of Chriſtianitie; which out of the Church are not to be found, either in Paganiſme, Iudaiſme, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometiſme. Were Hereſies and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions weeded out of the Church of Rome, the Remainder would bee Chriſtianiſme. For Poperie, is the diſeaſe of the Church, not the Church it ſelfe: and as the Leproſie, or other deadly Contagion is to the Body of a Man, ſuch is Poperie to the Body of the Catholicke Church: ſo that to forſake Poperie, is not to forſake the Church but the Plague of the Church. When an Ethnike is made a Chriſtian, an Alien and Forreyner is endenized and ingraffed into a new People, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be a Member of the Church: In the Reformation; an adulterous Church becomes a chaſt Spouſe, and is reconciled to Chriſt her Husband: and ſpurious and baſtard Chriſtians
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12623:26"/>are legitimated: wherefore, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Goods of her Husbands, the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſe vſurped; the lawfull Church (as the true Wife) may iuſtly clayme. In the <hi>Code</hi> of <hi>Theodoſius, Lib.</hi> 16. <hi>tit.</hi> 44. <hi>Contra Donatiſtas;</hi> it is thus. Let thoſe Poſſeſſions where direfull Superſtition hath hither to raigned, be annext to the Venerable Catholike Church: and let the Biſhops, Prieſts, and all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and Miniſters [of the Donatiſts] be ſtript of all their Reuenewes, and baniſht to ſeuerall Ilands, and Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. In the ſame place (in the 4 Booke) wee find a Decree of the Emperours <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> againſt the Montaniſts, in theſe words. If there be now any of their Edifices ſtanding, which are rather to be tearmed the Dennes of wild Beaſts, then Churches, let them with their Reuenewes be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the ſacred Churches of the Orthodox Faith.</p>
                     <p>Before our time there fell out many Alterations in the Church: but when
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12623:27"/>godly Emperors expelled the heretical partie; they ſpoyled not their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of their Poſſeſſions, but reſtored them to the true Profeſſors: as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> witneſſes in his 50 Epiſtle to <hi>Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facius</hi> a Souldier. <hi>Quicquid ergó, nomine Eccleſiarum partis Donati poſsidebatur, Chriſtiani Imperatores legibus religioſis cum ipſis Eccleſiis ad Catholicam tranſire iuſſerunt:</hi> That is, Whatſoeuer the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts poſſeſt in Right of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; the Chriſtian Emperors, by reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Lawes commanded to paſſe (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Churches) to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church. Thus <hi>Auſtin.</hi> I need not produce any more witneſſes to proue ſo euident a Thing, and well knowne. To capitulate therefore what hath beene ſayd: Eccleſiaſticall Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions gotten by fraud or force, and vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped againſt all Right, or giuen at firſt to a meere ſuperſtitious end, are in the power of the chiefe Magiſtrate. But what hath lawfully beene giuen to the Church, and receaned, is conſecrated
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12623:27"/>to God, nor may without Sacriledge be otherwiſe tranſ-ferred. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 50 Tract vpon <hi>Iohn,</hi> the 12 Chapter and 9 Tome, ſaith thus. <hi>Ecce inter Sanctos est Iudas, &amp;c.</hi> Behold <hi>Iudas</hi> among the Saints, and ſleight it not: not an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, but a ſacrilegious Theefe: a pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of purſes: but they were the Lords: of purſes, but ſuch as were ſacred. As Crimes are adiudged in the Ciuill Court, ſimple Theft (from priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) is not ſo penall, as to robbe the Common-wealth: How much more then is that ſacrilegious Theefe to bee condemned, which dare ſteale from the Church? Such a one may well be compared to <hi>Iudas,</hi> the ſonne of Perdition.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:12623:28"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VIII. </hi>What a haynous and incurable Sinne is Sacriledge.</head>
                     <p>PLATO being about to make a Law againſt Sacriledge,
<note place="margin">De Leg. Dial. 9.</note> begins with a great Preface, iudging it to be an incurable Cryme, and the Actor thereof not to be ordinarily euil, but a creature compoſed of inexpiable Villanies: wherefore hee exhorts ſuch as are led with that helliſh furie, to expiate themſelues, to frequent the Temples, to propitiate the Gods, to vſe the Companie of good Men, to giue eare to them, and to endeuour to ſpeake and practiſe honeſt and iuſt things. And if none of theſe can rid them of their diſeaſe, he holds, that Death were better for ſuch, then Life. The Tenour of his Law followeth. <hi>Quicun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> in Sacrilegio, &amp;c.</hi> Whoſoeuer
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12623:28"/>ſhall be found guiltie of Sacriledge, if he be a Seruant or Stranger, let his Crime be branded in his face &amp; hands, and being well ſcourged, according as the Iudges ſhall thinke meet, let him be ſtript naked, and ſo baniſht the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. For peraduenture he may become ſome-what the better by this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For no puniſhment that is infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, is hurtfull to the partie; but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther makes him better; or leſſe euill then he was. But if he be a Natiue or Citizen that ſhall be conuict of ſuch a Crime againſt the Gods, or ſhall doe ſome haynous iniurie to his Parents, or Citie, let the Iudge reſolue, that ſuch a one is incurable, ſince hauing had (from a Child) all Inſtitution and Education, he hath not contained himſelfe from the execution of ſuch execrable Acts. Let him therefore ſuffer Death; which is the leaſt of Euils. The other; being diſgraced and baniſhed, may haply doe good to others, by his Exemplarie pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie.</p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12623:29"/>
                     <p>The Romane Lawes of the twelue Tables, thus Decree concerning Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>Sacrum, ſacroue commendatum, qui clepſerit rapſerit<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> parricido eſto.</hi> That is, Hee that ſteales or takes away that which is ſacred; or dedicated to a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred vſe, let him be guiltie of Parricide. What ſhould I ſtand to repeat the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie of Lawes in this caſe? It is well knowne to all.</p>
                     <p>As for thoſe Sacrilegious perſons, which eſcape the Iudgement of Men, either becauſe they are Great, or Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull; or ſo concealed, as the Lawes cannot bee executed vpon them, they ſhall not be able to euade the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. For it is one of the moſt Capitall Crimes that is purſued with Diuine Reuenge: and both ſacred and prophane Stories yeeld vs innumerable Examples thereof: of which, I will propound a few.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12623:29"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IX. </hi>Examples of Gods Vengeance vpon ſacrilegious Perſons.</head>
                     <p>THE firſt Example, ſhall be that of <hi>Achan (Ioſua</hi> 7) who from the conſecrated Stuffe of <hi>Ieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho,</hi> tooke 200 ſhekels of Siluer, and a Wedge of Gold
<note n="*" place="margin">Ioſ. 6.19.</note> (beſide the accurſed Babyloniſh Garment) for whoſe onely ſinne, all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſuffered the Wrath of God, till the ſacrilegious Delinquent and all his Family; his Sonnes and Daughters, Oxen, Aſſes, and Sheepe were ſtoned to death by all the People; and afterwards (together with his Tent and all that he had) burned with fire. The next, ſhall be another ſacrilegious Fact committed by Prieſts, and puniſht by God, as ſeuerely as that of <hi>Achan.</hi> In 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. we read, <hi>That a Man of God came to Eli the High-Prieſt, and ſayd vnto
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12623:30"/>him, Thus ſaith the Lord, Did I plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto the Houſe of thy Father, when they were in Agypt in Pharaohs Houſe? And did I chuſe him out of all the Tribes of Iſrael, to be my Prieſt to offer vpon my Altar, to burne Incenſe, to weare an Ephod before mee? And did I giue vnto the Houſe of thy Father all the Offerings made by fire of the Children of Iſrael? Wherefore kicke ye at my Sacrifice, and at my offerings which I haue commanded in my Habitation, and honourest thy Sonnes aboue me, to make your ſelues fat with the obiefeſt of all the Offerings of Iſrael my People? Wherefore the Lord God of Iſraeh ſaith, I ſaid indeed, that thy Houſe, and the Houſe of thy Father ſhould walke before me for euer: But now the Lord ſaith, Be it farre from me: For them that honor Me, I will honor; and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed. Behold, the daies come, that I will cut off thine arme and the arme of thy Fathers Houſe, that there ſhall not bee an old Man in thine Houſe. And thou ſhalt ſee an Enemie in my Habitation, in all the Wealth which God
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12623:30"/>ſhall giue Iſrael, and there ſhall not be an old Man in thine Houſe for euer. And the Man of thine, whom I ſhall not cut off from mine Altar, ſhall be to conſume thine Eyes, and to grieue thine Heart; and all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of thine Houſe ſhall dye in the flowre of their age. And this ſhall be a ſigne vnto thee, that ſhall come vpon thy two Sonnes, on</hi> Hophni <hi>and</hi> Phinehas: <hi>in one day they ſhall dye both of them. And I will rayſe me vp a faithfull Prieſt, that ſhall doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which is in mine Heart, and in my mind, and I will build him a ſure Houſe, and he ſhall walke before mine Anointed for euer. And it ſhall come to paſſe, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one that is left in thine Houſe, ſhall come and crouch to him for a piece of Siluer, and a morſell of Bread, and ſhall ſay, Put me (I pray thee) into one of the Priests offices, that I may eat a piece of Bread.</hi> Thus the Man of God: All which things, as hee foretold them, ſoone after came to paſſe. For the Sonnes of <hi>Eli</hi> were ſlain in Battell: The Arke of the Couenant was taken by prophane Men: <hi>Eli</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12623:31"/>heard the meſſage thereof, fell from his Seat, and brake his necke, and dyed: His Daughter-in-law <hi>(Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nehas</hi> Wife) dyed in the pangs of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth: The holy place of <hi>Shiloh</hi> was forſaken of God, nor was the Arke of God euer brought thither againe: Laſtly by <hi>Sauls</hi> appointment, 85 Prieſts (of <hi>Eli's</hi> Family) were put to the ſword. I omit to ſpeake of other calamities which that Houſe ſuffered, for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge of thoſe two Perſons. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> did (after a ſort) honorably entertaine the ſacred Arke, yet did God ſeuerely puniſh their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie, nor did they ſcape ſcotfree for handling ſo diuine a thing. I paſſe by the Sacriledges committed, from that time, to the Captiuitie of <hi>Babylon. Balthuſar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> is a memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Example of Diuine Iuſtice againſt the Sacrilegious. For hee commanded that the ſacred Veſſels which his grand father <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> had taken out of the Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſhould bee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12623:31"/>ſhould be brought to the Feaſt which hee had made, that Himſelfe and his Gueſts might drinke therein in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God. But the Wrath of God ſeized vpon the ſacrilegious Prince, in the very Act, and denounced to him preſent Deſtruction by the Prodigie of a Hand-writing on the Wall of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. Whereupon <hi>Daniel</hi> the Seruant of God being called to read and interpret that diuine Writ, did grauely rebuke him for his Impietie; ſaying to him (among other things) thus: <hi>Thou hast lifted vp thy ſelfe against the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and they haue brought the Veſſels of his Houſe before thee, and Thou and thy Lords, thy wiues and thy Concubines haue drunke Wine in them, and thou haſt prayſed the Gods of Siluer and Gold, of Braſſe, Iron, Wood, and Stone, which ſee not, nor heare, nor know: and the God in whoſe hand thy breath is, and whoſe are all thy wayes, haſt thou not glorified. Then was the part of the Hand ſent from him, and this Writing was written:</hi> Mene, Mene, Tekel, Vpharſin.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12623:32"/>
                        <hi>This is the Interpretation of the thing,</hi> Mene, <hi>God hath aumbred thy Kingdome, and finiſhed it.</hi> Tekel, <hi>Thou are weighed in the Balances, and art found wanting.</hi> Vpharſin, <hi>Thy Kingdome is diuided, and giuen to the Meedes and Perſians.</hi> Thus <hi>Daniel.</hi> And that very night was <hi>Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> ſlaine, and the Empire of the <hi>Aſsiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Chaldaeans,</hi> which had flouriſhed 130 yeeres, ended, and was giuen by God to the <hi>Meedes</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I come now to the <hi>Greekes,</hi> vnder whom the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſuffered many grieuous calamities, both from their owne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the <hi>Greekes</hi> themſelues. The execrable Fact of <hi>Altimus</hi> the High-Prieſt, which ſought to ouerthrow the Temple of God, was not vnpuniſhed: for being ſtrucked with a Palſie, he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in great torment. <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> being ſent to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by King <hi>Seleucus,</hi> to rob the Temple, of the ſacred Treaſure (which hee vnderſtood, was exceeding much) felt the hand of God vpon him; together with his Companions which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12623:32"/>came with him: nor had he eſcaped Death, if <hi>Onias</hi> the Prieſt had not pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God for him. Whereupon, being deliuered, he returned to his King, and profeſt, that God was the Keeper of that Temple, and Defender of the Treaſure: and if the King were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with any, and wiſhed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, he ſhould ſend him thither. The robbing of that Temple, coſt that great Romane Commander <hi>M. Craſſus</hi> deere: for God, by the <hi>Perſians,</hi> reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Sacriledge: who put him, and his Army to the Sword; and thruſt molten Gold (which in his life-time he ſo thirſted after) into his head &amp; mouth and in inſulting manner, exprobrated his vnſatiable Auarice. <hi>Iudas</hi> the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, deſerues the firſt place among ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Wretches; for hee, for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerouſneſſe of Gold, ſpared not his Lord and Maſter, whom he knew to be innocent. But he became his owne Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, Iudge, and Hangman; and ſo miſerably periſhed. Admirable alſo is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12623:33"/>the Example of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphyra;</hi> whom God chaſtened with corporall Death, becauſe they preſumed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to their owne vſe, part of that Money which themſelues had volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily dedicated to God. Which Fact of theirs, though it were more excuſable, then if they had done ſo with others Money; yet wee ſee the ſeueritie of Gods Iudgement vpon them; to the Terror of all other Chriſtians.</p>
                     <p>All Hiſtories relate the Plagues which fell vpon <hi>Iulian</hi> the Emperour, for his Apoſtacie and Sacriledge: who in deriſion of Chriſt and Chriſtians: when he had ſtript the Church and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of all they had, told them, that in ſo doing, he had a ſpeciall care of their Soules health; becauſe the Goſpell commended Pouertie vnto them.</p>
                     <p>To this <hi>Iulian,</hi> I will adde another <hi>Iulian;</hi> his Vnckle; as ſacrilegious a miſcreant, as himſelfe: who at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> hauing gotten together a great number of moſt precious Veſſels and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12623:33"/>lewels of the Church, to carrie them into the Emperours Treaſurie; hee threw them on the Ground, and began to ſcorne and blaſpeme Chriſt at his pleaſure; at laſt, he ſat downe (in great contempt) vpon the ſacred Veſſels. But ſee the hand of God! Straight after, his Priuie-members, and ſecret-parts conſumed away, and the Fleſh about them rotting by peece-meale, turned into Vermine: and his Diſeaſe ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, that no Phyſicke could helpe him: for the Vermine, being hid in his Inward-parts, crept to his ſound and liue fleſh, and neuer ceaſed gnawing, till they had quite made an end of him.</p>
                     <p>I omit others, whom the Wrath of God hath puniſhed in like ſort.</p>
                     <p>Many Hiſtories of Chriſtian Kings might be added, whom God iuſtly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued for their Sacriledges: but that it were too tedious a worke: and ſome things are reputed by Hiſtorians, for ſacriledgious; which if they were done in no contempt of God, may be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12623:34"/>excuſable. It had beene ſacriledge in <hi>Dauid,</hi> to haue eaten the Shew-bread, if Neceſſitie had not excuſed it. But ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge is to be meaſured by Impiety; which conſiſts as well in the Contempt of a falſe God, as of the true; to wit, whenſoeuer, that, which othersworſhip (for God) is contemned with a kind of Irreligion; rather; then out of a true Faith, and deuotion to the true God. And ſo much, is the mind and intent, in this caſe, to be conſidered; that as it may be an Act of pietie in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of the true God, to demoliſh the Temples of falſe Gods; and to breake their Images: ſo, if the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of falſe Gods; or Atheiſts, which ſcorne all Gods; ſhould doe the like, it were Sacriledge, and Impietie.</p>
                     <p>If any aske, how he can be ſayd to contemne God, which beleeues there is no God?</p>
                     <p>I anſwer, His very beleeuing that there is none, proceeds from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:12623:34"/>
                     <p>No meruaile therefore, if the wrath of God fell vpon Idolaters that were ſacriledgious. Whereof prophane Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries haue innumerable examples, of which I will ſelect a few.</p>
                     <p>The Temple of <hi>Delphos</hi> was famous in the World; and neither <hi>Xerxes,</hi> nor <hi>Brennus</hi> that prophaned it could eſcape the viſible vengeance of God. The Prouerbe of the Gold of <hi>Tholouze;</hi> whence it had its originall, is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cambyſes</hi> Souldiers which he ſent to robbe the Temple of <hi>Iupiter Ammon,</hi> were ſwallowed vp quicke of great heapes of Sand: and <hi>Cambyſes</hi> himſelfe a derider of the Aegyptian ſacrifices, becauſe he did it, out of an Impions mind (notwithſtanding they were defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſuperſtition) not long after that hee had killed their Oxe-God <hi>Apis,</hi> periſhed of a wound giuen him with his owne Dagger.</p>
                     <p>And the Wrath of God (in all mens Iudgement) lighted on <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12623:35"/>hauing robd the Treaſurie of <hi>Proſerpina</hi> the <hi>Locrenſian</hi> Goddeſſe, and hauing conueyed that wicked Prize to his Ships, himſelfe and all his Fleet with a ſudden ſtorme were drowned neere to the bordering ſhore; where the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was all taken vp, and reſtored to the Goddeſſes Treaſurie.</p>
                     <p>I will adde one more Example of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant of <hi>Syracuſa</hi> (though of contrarie Euent) for their ſakes that among their Companions thinke it ſuch good ſport to laugh at God, and all Religion, to the end that they which ſcorne the Doctrine of Chriſtianitie, may be inſtructed by Pagans themſelus. <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> in his firſt Booke and ſecond Chapter, Of the neglect of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; relates theſe words of <hi>Tully</hi> concerning <hi>Dionyſius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dionyſius</hi> borne at <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> did take great pleaſure in ieſting at his ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious prankes, which we now reherſe.</p>
                     <p>Hauing robbed the Temple of the <hi>Locrenſian Proſerpina,</hi> and ſayling after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12623:35"/>with a very proſperous wind, he ſmiled and ſayd to his Friends: See ye not with what a fayre gale of wind the Gods themſelues bleſſe them at Sea, which robbe them? Another time, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſtript the Statue of <hi>Iupiter Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> of a goodly Garment of maſſie Gold, which King <hi>Hiero</hi> hauing taken from the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> did adorne it with; he put on (in ſtead thereof) a Cloath-cloke, ſaying, that a Golden-Mantle was too heauie for Summer, and too cold for Winter; but that of Cloath would ſerue very fitly for both ſeaſons. He commanded alſo to take away the golden Beard of <hi>Aſculapius</hi> at <hi>Epidaurus;</hi> ſaying, that it was vndecent to ſee the Sonne haue a Beard, &amp; <hi>Apollo,</hi> the Father to haue none. He tooke alſo the Golden and Siluer Tables out of the Temples; and becauſe it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in them (after the <hi>Greeke</hi> faſhion) that they were the Tables of the good Gods, he ſayd, he would make vſe of their Goodneſſe. He alſo tooke away
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12623:36"/>the golden Plates, Crownes, &amp; Images of Victorie, which were held with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched hands of Images of the Gods; ſaying, that he did not take them away, but receaue what was offered him: ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, that it was a ſenſeleſſe thing, to pray to the Gods for good things, and refuſe them when they ſo readily ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them. This man, though in his own perſon he ſuffered according to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, yet being dead, he had that penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by the ignominie of his Sonne, which hee eſcaped when hee was aliue. For God proceeds many times but ſlowly to reuenge: yet at laſt, that ſlowneſſe is recompenced with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter weight of puniſhment. Thus farre <hi>Valerius;</hi> who though he ſay much, yet much more is ſayd by <hi>Tully,</hi> to wit, that Tyrants are euer vexed with the Sting of Conſcience;
<note place="margin">Lib. 3. De Nat. Deo.</note> and that their wicked Acts neuer let them reſt, but inwardly torment their Minds, euen as Hangmen torture Malefactors on the Wheele or Racke, And certainely
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12623:36"/>
                        <hi>Dionyſius</hi> his laughter was but <hi>Sardonian</hi> (as they ſay) and from the teeth out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: for being conſcious of ſo much Villanie, he could not poſſibly be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare. And though the Vulgar might thinke him a happy man, yet he knew himſelfe, how wretched he was, and how farre from his ſuppoſed Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.
<note place="margin">Cic. lib. 4. Tuſe.</note> His friend <hi>Damocles</hi> being deſirous to haue a Taſt of his happy Eſtate; hee was content: and commanded him to be placed in a Golden Bed, and all kind of Delicates to be miniſtred to him: ſo that <hi>Damocles</hi> thought himſelfe moſt happy. But as ſoone as he perceaued a glittering Sword ouer his head, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Roofe but by a Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hayre, inſtantly the pleaſure he tooke in all thoſe ſweet things, vaniſhed: and being loth to enioy a happineſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſuch fearfull perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hee craued leaue of the Tyrant to be gone. And hath not <hi>Dionyſius</hi> now ſufficiently ſhewed in what fearfull pangs the Sacrilegious are?</p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:12623:37"/>
                     <p>But what ſhall we ſay to that of the Satyriſt?</p>
                     <q xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Dicite Pontifices,</l>
                        <l>in Templo quid facit aurum?</l>
                     </q>
                     <q xml:lang="eng">
                        <l>Tell me, you High-Prieſts,</l>
                        <l>what makes Gold here i'the Temple?</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>It is no reaſon that I ſhould reply in behalfe of thoſe Pagan-Prieſts: Yet thus much I dare ſay; That Gold, ſuch as it was, to the impious Idolaters, was ſacred. What vſe that ſerued for, which was kept in the Temple of God, wee may know by the words of <hi>Onias</hi> the High-Prieſt to <hi>Heliodorus:</hi> to wit, for the reliefe of Widowes and Orphans. As for the Treaſure and Gold which once the Church had, it was not, in the beſt times, vnemployed; but was vſed for the ſupply of poore neceſſitated Chriſtians, and people that were in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie. The Church (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) hath Gold, which it hoords not, but beſtowes, as occaſion ſerues.</p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:12623:37"/>
                     <p>It was euer the chiefeſt Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a Biſhop, to feed the poore, and helpe the afflicted: and becauſe Chriſtians in times paſt would haue their Biſhops to be bountifull, they did endow them with large Reuenewes. But now Men ſeeke to vndoe them, and to reduce them to ſuch a poore pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as they can verie hardly ſupport their eſtates. So, they may teach Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and preach Liberalitie, but not be able to practiſe it. I well wot, that ſome will obiect the Couetouſneſſe, and Pompe of Biſhops, and that they ſpend all the Churches wealth on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, without any Care or Conſcience to releeue the Poore with any part of it: which Sacriledge, if it be found in Men of their Ranke, is a great deale the more heynous. But one Sacriledge cannot excuſe another: and leaſt the Paſtors of Churches ſhould commit Sacriledge, they which haue impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Church-Liuing, had rather doe it themſelues.</p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:12623:38"/>
                     <p>For moſt certaine it is, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer (vnder that colour) hath beene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Church, hath not beene giuen to the Poore: who are now in worſe caſe, then euer before: yea they were farre better releeued by Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall perſons, heretofore; then now by Lay-men (of what qualitie ſoeuer) that haue gotten the Lands of the Church into their poſſeſſion: And when the Tyrannie of the Biſhop of Rome was firſt aboliſhed, the Poore might with more eaſe haue obtained their due portion from the Paſtors of the Church, then euer they could from them which vniuſtly ſucceeded them, and ſtill vſurpe the Churches Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. But to conclude, whoſoeuer they bee that either make a prey of the Church, or wickedly abuſe the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes thereof, cannot be excuſed from the Crime of Sacriledge, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (without Reſtitution) ſhall not eſcape the Vengeance of GOD.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:12623:38"/>
                     <head>
                        <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Reaſons against the Maintenance of Miniſters by arbitrarie Stipends.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing the Apoſtolike Rule commands, that good Order be kept in the Church, and that all things therein bee done to Edification; it is not amiſſe to conſider, whether it may better bee obſerued, by putting Miniſters to Penſions, or by the ancient manner of paying Tithes and Offerings to the Paſtors, deliuered by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to the People of God, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Fathers of the Church. I ſuppoſe, that Wiſedome was not borne with vs, that wee ſhould order things better, then the Ancients did: and I hold that wee ought to innouate
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12623:39"/>nothing in the Church, without the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued patterne of former times, to the end wee giue no iuſt cauſe to our Aduerſaries to calumniate. But this new found way of honoring the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie with Stipendarie Contributions, is vnknowne to the Scriptures, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: for it was neuer heard of before our time, that the Church had ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie Miniſters. Yet I would not be ſo miſtaken, as if I held it vtterly vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the Magiſtrate to allow Penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Clergie for their better maintenance: but this I ſay, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian People are bound to their Paſtors in a more ſtrickt and religious Bond of Obſeruance; and therefore it is their dutie, by the beſt Expreſſions of a gratefull mind, to honor them: which when they doe not, it is a ſigne, their Charitie is but cold.
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>al. 6.6.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Paul</hi> commands that he which is taught in the Word, communicate vnto his Teacher in all his Goods: From which Dutie no ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends can free the Rich and Wealthy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12623:39"/>hearers. For that Communication of good things is not alwayes done for the releeuing of neceſſitie, but alſo for the Teſtification of our thankfull and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Regard. Our poore Chriſtian Brother is honoured with a reward, for his neceſſitie: but, the Paſtor, for his Office and Dignitie. Againe, the Will of Magiſtrate is mutable; whom if Miniſters chance to diſpleaſe, they are ſure to haue but ſlow payment, and perhaps none at all. And if their Penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons come from the publike Treaſurie; whenſoeuer that is at an Ebbe (as many times it happens) they are like to be in a pittifull caſe. For the People being not wont to pay any thing (of due Right) to their Paſtor, will thinke that his Neceſſitie is nothing to them; and will not therefore be perſwaded, to do as Dutie binds them: yea, the moſt will rather vtterly forſake their Preacher, then contribute any thing to him: who being ſo deſerted, will bee forced to leaue his Flocke: as in many places of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12623:40"/>
                        <hi>Holland,</hi> it hath come to paſſe. And how miſerable the eſtate of Miniſters is in <hi>Holland;</hi> both for ſmalneſſe of Stipend, and difficultie of payment, they know who haue experience of it; being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to goe a long and tedious way to begge their Pay of the Officers; who oft welcomming them with baſe reproches, ſend them away emptie: ſo that they bring home nought, beſide the troubleſomneſſe of their Iourney, but loſſe of Time and Expence. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the Magiſtrates that are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to pay ſuch Stipends, begin to eſteeme their Paſtors, but as Ciuill Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers: inſomuch, that men of baſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition (ſetting their Office aſide) as Shoomakers, Smithes, Woodmongers and Pedling Merchants dare many times preſume to inſult moſt rudely ouer their Preachers: ſaying, you are our Seruants; we pay you Wages, &amp;c. I ſhould be aſhamed to ſpeake ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly, to a Drudge, or Scul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:12623:40"/>
                     <p>Being at a ſolemne Feaſt at <hi>Gaunt,</hi> where the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, I ſat ouer againſt two Scabines, or Burgomaſters, who when they had well warmed themſelues with Wine, and of Mutes, were become Vowels, thinking (belike) that I heard not what they ſayd, being buſie in talke with him that ſat next me, they fell (as I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) into this Diſcourſe.</p>
                     <p>We muſt (ſayd they) take heed leſt theſe Miniſters doe not ſometime put vs to as much trouble, as the Popes did. We muſt therefore keepe them vnder, that they grow not into too much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and authoritie with the People, to the preiudice of the Magiſtrate: and eſpecially wee muſt ſee that their Stipends bee not great; for hee that daintily feeds his Seruant, ſhall find him refractarie.</p>
                     <p>Theſe Men made a ſhew to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous (forſooth) of the Church, and Defenders thereof, but afterwards they diſcouered themſelues what they were,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12623:41"/>prouing indeed Traytors to the Church and Countrey. Whether <hi>Holland</hi> haue any more ſuch, I know not: From like effects, it is lawfull to argue to the like cauſes.</p>
                     <p>Thus wee ſee, that the Temporalties of the Church being confiſcate, or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegiouſly alienated, there can accrew nothing to the Clergie, from their new ſupercilious Pay-Maſters, but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
                     <p>Let none therefore wonder, if I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like this new fangled way of honoring and maintayning the Miniſters of the Goſpel: for it is no honour, which is ioyned with Diſgrace. And let that Order which was preſcribed by God himſelfe out of his Diuine Wiſdome, in the Old and New Teſtament, for the honorable maintenance of his Seruants, as it was vnderſtood and practiſed by the ancient Fathers, be inuiolably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued: nor let ſelfe-conceit flatter vs, that wee are able to find out a better way. Let Abuſes be ſo corrected, that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12623:41"/>the lawfull vſe be reſtored: and let not their Impietie which with their wicked Acts defiled ſacred &amp; prophane things, ſo farre tranſport vs, as to confound ſacred and prophane together; and vtterly aboliſh that difference in Things, which Nature and Reaſon haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:42"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:42"/>
                  <p>AN APPENDIX TO <hi>SARAVIA;</hi> ANSWERING FOVRE MAINE Arguments which Vſurpers of the Churches Right vſually <hi>alledge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <q>POST TENEBRAS LVX</q>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Cotes</hi> and <hi>R. Cotes</hi> for <hi>Iames Boler,</hi> 1629.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:43"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:43"/>
                  <head>An Appendix to SARAVIA; Anſwering foure maine Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which Vſurpers of the Churches Rights vſually <hi>alledge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="argument">
                     <head>First, Abbey-Land.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Land is Abbey-Land, belonging to ſuch a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterie before the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: and conſequently exempted from Tithes, as was the Abbey.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>This Land they may enioy, vnleſſe it were once conſecrated to the Church: and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12623:44"/>if ſo, let them take heed: for what is once dedicated to the ſeruice of God, may not be alienated there-from: (ſome few caſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) whereof this (of Lay-impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors) is none.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="reply">
                        <head>Their Reply.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It is deſcended to vs by Inheritance, and therefore we may without ſcruple enioy it.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1</hi> It is very diſputable whether their Title be cleere, vnleſſe it can be euidently proued by them, that the Land was neuer conſecrated to God, (as aforeſayd,) which if it be not apparent, they cannot without much doubting, and ſcruple of Conſcience, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy it.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2</hi> Admit, their Title bee cleere, and themſelues void of perplexitie concerning it; yet was the Tithe of thoſe Lands ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally conſecrated to the maintenance of Gods Seruice: Why then deny they the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Tithe? For it is not a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12623:44"/>Penſion (in lieu thereof) that will maintaine a ſufficient Preacher, or will excuſe them for detayning it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="rejoinder">
                        <head>Their Reioynder.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The ſame Parliamentarie Authority which giues Miniſters Tithe in Places not exempted, hath exempted our lands from payment of Tithe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>But what if the Law (in that point) be not ſo cleere as they imagine? It is well-knowne, that the alienation of theſe Tithes (deuolued to the King at the diſſolution of Abbeys, together with the Lands) was at first, an Act of the Pope, by iniurious vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation vpon the Churches Right, &amp; againſt the Lawes of God and Man then in force. Now it is not to be thought, that the Statute (in that caſe) intended the ratification of that ſacrilegious Act, or to make that iust which is originally vniuſt, or vtterly to aboliſh Tithes; but onely to change the poſſeſsion, for the preſent, till the Churches
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12623:45"/>claime might more euidently appeare. But ſuppoſe the Law were cleere for non-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe Tithes, how doth it accord with the patterne of the Diuine Law? For if God haue ordained that Preachers of the Goſpel ſhould liue of the Goſpel, and that their Hearers are to communicate vnto them
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> in all good things; then ſurely, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Miniſterie is much more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then that of the Law, either Tithes (at leſt) or ſome better thing is due to them by Diuine Ordinance. It is therefore hard dealing, to barre them of the ancient Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Tithe, vnleſſe there can be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of Scripture ſome other Law of Prouiſion, to diſanull it.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="argument">
                     <head>Second, Compoſition.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WEE haue Compoſitions from former Incumbents which free vs from Tithes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>Though ſuch Compoſitions be ſeldome
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12623:45"/>produced, leſt the preſent Miniſter may picke ſomewhat out thereof, for his owne aduantage and reliefe, yet admit the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition be neuer ſo ſtrong, how can it ſtand with Conſcience, that the Act of one Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ſhould preiudice his Succeſſours in a great Charge, to their vtter impoue, iſhment and vndoing? Or how can it be reputea a lawfull Contract, which ſo deeply trenches on the Churches Right, to the extreme decay and hinderance of Gods Seruice? Can the buyer or ſeller (in this caſe) haue any hope to be a member of the Church Triumphant, that liues and dyes a betrayer and ſpoyler of the Church militant, in that ſort? Better therefore, that ſuch Compoſitions be renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, then their Soules be ſo manifestly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="argument">
                     <head>Third, Praeſcription.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WEE can proue Praeſcription (for diners Deſcents) exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs from Tithes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:12623:46"/>
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>It is obſerued, that few great rich-men can indure with patience to pay Tithe in kind: whereupon they take their opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to agree with the Incumbents for their Tithe at an vnder-value; pretending, that if they agree not, they will make the Tithe little worth to them: this done, they are willing, out of their (exceeding) Zeale to the Church, to allow a poore yeerely Penſion to the Preacher. Which Praeſcription hauing once got footing for ſome good tearme of yeeres; if any ſucceeding Incumbent dare preſume to question it, they will make him know, that hee hath rowzed a Lyon, and ſcourge him through all the Courts of the Kingdome. Yea, if the Preſcribers adde, by purchaſe, or incloſure, to their Demaines in the ſame Pariſh; they will by vertue of the ſame vicious Preſcription, detaine all the Tithe of the Portion ſo annext. The anſwer therefore is, <hi>Non firmatur tractu tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris, quod de iure ab initio non ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtit:</hi> That which was of no validitie at
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12623:46"/>the beginning, neuer becomes lawfull by any tract of Time. This therefore is nothing but a plaine robbing of the Churches due.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="argument">
                     <head>Fourth, Cuſtomes.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>BY the Cuſtome of our Pariſh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by long conſent, and practiſe time out of mind, we pay not ſuch and ſuch Tithes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>Conſent and Practiſe make not a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome lawfull, vnleſſe it be grounded vpon euident reaſonable cauſe: <hi>Niſi enim, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo ratione munita ſit, non eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo, ſed corruptela:</hi> If Custome be not fortified by Reaſon, it is rather Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then Cuſtome. By which Rule, if the pretended Customes be examined; they will (for the moſt part,) appeare both vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and vnconſcionable: for if the greateſt part of the Pariſh be Wood-ground, is it not reaſon that Tithe-Wood be payd? And if
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12623:47"/>Sheepe feed on the Common for eight the most profitable months in the yeere, though they be not wintered in the Field, is there any Reaſon to detaine the Tithe, vpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Cuſtome?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="reply">
                        <head>Their Reply.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Notwithſtanding, wee pay to the Miniſter, a proportionable Rate.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>True: if a few ſcraps, not worth taking vp, may be ſo tearmed: which how it may ſtand, with Right or Reaſon, Iuſtice or Equitie, let all men (that are not partiall) iudge.</p>
                        <p>Seeing therefore, that theſe Exemptions, Compoſitions, Praeſcriptions, and Cuſtomes, are the very Cankers of the Church, and bring infinite penurie, and miſerie vpon the Clergie, to the extreme decay, &amp; detriment of Gods true Religion; I ſee not how they can be ſaid to haue any ſenſe or feeling of God, or Godlineſſe, that ſhall, against the Euidence of Truth, and recoyling of their Conſcience, continue them.</p>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:12623:47"/>
                        <closer>
                           <hi>The LORD turne the Hearts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>he Spoylers of his Inheritance; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> remember in mercie thoſe which haue compaſſion on his diſtreſſed Seruants.</hi>
                        </closer>
                        <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="addition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:48"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:48"/>
                  <head>Additionals.</head>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>X</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>EXprimit antiquis</l>
                        <l>haec Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s littera ſcriptis,</l>
                        <l>Exprimit &amp; partem</l>
                        <l>quam petit ille ſacram.</l>
                        <l>Ergo citus, Christi quae ſuut,</l>
                        <l>dato munera Chriſto:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Caeſaris</hi> accipiat <hi>Caeſar:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>vter<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſuum.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>H. S.</hi> Eques Auratus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Thus Engliſhed.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THis X (of old)</l>
                        <l>expreſt Chriſts holy Name,</l>
                        <l>And eke the ſacred Tenth,</l>
                        <l>which he doth claime:</l>
                        <l>Giue then to CHRIST,</l>
                        <l>what's CHRIST's, without delay:</l>
                        <l>Giue <hi>Caeſar, Caeſar</hi>'s due:</l>
                        <l>and Both, their Pay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>I. A. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:12623:49"/>
                     <head>In modernos <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; Numularios; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SOme ſay, ſince <hi>Peter</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>cut off <hi>Malchus</hi> eare</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Clergie</hi> and the <hi>Lay</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>haue ſcarce beene friends:</l>
                        <l>But why ſhould they</l>
                        <l>ſuch cauſleſſe grudges beare?</l>
                        <l>Was there not inſtantly</l>
                        <l>made full amends?</l>
                        <l>Yet All (though ſtrong</l>
                        <l>and pond'rous Proofes they ſee</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Preſt on Church-Pirates)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>will not yet agree.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For <hi>Simon Magus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>in a <hi>ſacred</hi> thirst</l>
                        <l>After <hi>Church-Liuings</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>(taking <hi>Malchus</hi> part)</l>
                        <l>With his <hi>Bore</hi>-ſpeare</l>
                        <l>(O Caitife moſt accurst!)</l>
                        <l>Runnes <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>and <hi>Iohn</hi> into the heart:</l>
                        <l>Yea, all their Succeſſors</l>
                        <l>ſeeking to quell,</l>
                        <l>Or begger quite,</l>
                        <l>rides poſt amaine to Hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12623:49"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>After him marcheth</l>
                        <l>hungry <hi>Sacriledge</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>(Ye lad with mightie Armes,</l>
                        <l>and maſsie Shield)</l>
                        <l>Gainſt the poore <hi>Church;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>and proudly can alleage</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>CVSTOME</hi> and <hi>LAVV;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>then challengeth the Field.</l>
                        <l>But ſoft <hi>(S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> DAGONET)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>a word (I pray')</l>
                        <l>Ere that our <hi>Tithes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>you harry quite away.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Is not our <hi>GOSPEL</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>better then your <hi>LAVV?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>(Yea, or the <hi>Law</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſelfe did vtter:)</l>
                        <l>Is not that, <hi>Gold;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>and
<note n="*" place="margin">Caninum litigand ſtudium dixit Colu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mella. Lib. 1 In Procem.</note> yours (to it) but <hi>Straw?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>How dare you than</l>
                        <l>'gainst Preachers portions ſtutter?</l>
                        <l>Your Clowniſh <hi>CVSTOME</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>thus away we kicke;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hoc, ab initio</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>non fuit ſic.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12623:50"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If all this cannot</l>
                        <l>yet reclaime your Error</l>
                        <l>(Which doth the Tenth</l>
                        <l>to Iewiſh Temple bind,</l>
                        <l>Leauing the Chriſtian, free:)</l>
                        <l>then (to your terror)</l>
                        <l>A heauie Doome</l>
                        <l>you in this Booke ſhall find.</l>
                        <l>Acknowledge then,</l>
                        <l>our Tithes diuinely
<note n="*" place="margin">Iure diuine.</note> due:</l>
                        <l>To circumciſe vs thus,</l>
                        <l>you play the Iew.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>S. N.</hi> Theol. Oxon.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="verse">
                     <pb facs="tcp:12623:50"/>
                     <head>A Propheticall Complaint to God, againſt Church-Pirates and Vſurpers.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>PSAL. 80.13, 14.</bibl>
                        <p>The wild Bore out of the Wood, doth root it vp: and the wild Beaſt of the Field doth deuour it.</p>
                        <p>Turne thee againe thou GOD of Hoſts, looke downe from Heauen; behold, and viſit this Vine.</p>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="verse">
                     <head>The Churches Teares.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>LAMENTAT. 1.16.</bibl>
                        <p>For theſe things I weepe, mine eye, mine eye runneth down with water, becauſe the Comforter that ſhould relieue my Soule is farre from me: my Children are deſolate, becauſe the Enemie preuayled.</p>
                     </q>
                     <closer>VIVAT CHRISTVS: PEREAT BARABBAS.</closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:51"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12623:51"/>
                  <head>Operarum Errata.</head>
                  <p>Page 2. l. 23. read thruſt. p. 10. l. 18. r. Code. p. 23. l. 17. r. Paſtors. p 27. l. 17. f. a Mungrel and r. an (<hi>dele reliqua</hi>) p 33. l. 18. r. all good Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. p. 34. l. 4. r. parricida p. 44. l. 10. r. God. p. 45 l. 7. r. throughout the World. p. 48. l. 10. r. ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not. p. 55. l 9. r. Magiſtrates.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Lectori malè-feriato &amp; Nugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polyloquidi.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rode caper vites; tamen hìc cum flabis ad aras,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In tua quod fundi cornua poſsit, erit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
